A Guide to the Records of the Oakrum Baptist Church (Prince William County, Va.), 1883-1964
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Oakrum Baptist Church (Prince William County, Va.) 1883-1964
The Library of Virginia
41985
1 reel of microfilm
.70 cubic feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
For preservation reasons, please serve microfilm (Misc. reel 4846).
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Oakrum Baptist Church, Haymarket, Virginia, 3 June 2005.
Alternative Form Available
Miscellaneous reel 4846.
Biographical Information
Located in Thoroughfare, Prince William County, Virginia, the congregation was organized in 1865 at the home of Alexandra Johnson. The first meeting house was erected in 1883. In 1909 a new building was erected. At first named Little Zion, the name was changed to Oakrum Baptist Church of Thoroughfare. Rev. James Robinson, Rev. Hamilton, Brother Thornton Johnson, and Rev. Moses B. Strother served as the first ministers.
Scope and Content
Records, 1883-1964, of the Oakrum Baptist Church in Prince William County, Virginia. Includes record books, 1883-1903; roll books, 1901-1962; minute books, 1932-1958; and various loose papers. The loose papers include Anniversary booklets (100 and 130th); correspondence; information on the highway marker; savings pass books, 1946-1956; history; accounts; receipts; and resolutions.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically into two series.
Contents List
- Series I: Volumes
  - Record Book, 1883 - February 1894 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes minutes, roll, and accounts.
  - Record Book, 1894 - 1903 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Roll Book, 1901 - 1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Roll Book, 1930 - 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes Brothers Roll and Sisters Roll, listing names with amount of dues paid.
  - Roll Book, 1939 - 1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minute Book, 10 September 1932 - 11 May 1935 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minute Book, 13 July 1935 - 9 July 1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minute Book, 10 January 1942 - 11 January 1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    The minutes for 11 January 1947 are incomplete and are on the first page of the volume.
  - Minute Book, 26 February 1954 - 24 August 1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    This volume is not organized in chronological order. The 1954 minutes are in the back of the volume.
- Series II: Loose Papers
  - Anniversary Booklets (100th and 130th) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1931, 1932, 1962, 1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Highway Marker - "Free People of Color at Thoroughfare" (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1927, 1939, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Minutes for 8 January 1927 (includes 1926 annual reports); 8 July 1939; and undated fragment.
  - Savings Pass Books (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes August 1946 - October 1955; and October 1955 - April 1956.
  - Miscellaneous Loose Papers, 1925-1940 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Accounts, 1927, 1930, 1931, 1932
    Broadside for "Revival Services at Olive Branch Baptist Church.
    History of Oakrum Baptist Church From 1865 to 1962
    Receipts, 1931, 1936, 1940
    Resolutions
    Rolls and Dues Paid, 1925, 1932, 1933